<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hope of peace By laying open such doubts and manifest vntruthes as are divulged by the Arch-priest in his letter or answere to the bookes which were published by the priestes.</title>
            <author>Bennett, John, fl. 1588-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850493</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850493</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08522)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 654:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hope of peace By laying open such doubts and manifest vntruthes as are divulged by the Arch-priest in his letter or answere to the bookes which were published by the priestes.</title>
                  <author>Bennett, John, fl. 1588-1623.</author>
                  <author>Blackwell, George, 1546 or 7-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the heires of D. Turner [i.e. T. Creede],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Franckford [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: I.B. (i.e. John Bennett).</note>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes text of George Blackwell's letter.</note>
                  <note>"One in a series of controversial Catholic works, between the Arch-priest George Blackwell and the Jesuits on the one hand, and the secular priests on the other (the "appellant)."--Folger Shakespeare Library Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 1041.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HOPE of Peace.</p>
            <p>By laying open ſuch doubts and manifeſt vntruthes as are divulged by the Arch-prieſt in his Letter or Anſwere to the Bookes which were publiſhed by the Prieſtes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zacha.</hi> 8.</bibl>
               <p>Veritatem tantum &amp; pacem diligite.</p>
            </q>
            <q>Loue truth onely and Peace.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device(?) of a griffin seated upon a book</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at Franckford by the heires of D. Turner. 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:15701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15701:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo Bookes haue beene lately ſet foorth by the Prieſts in the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry defence of their good name and fame, which were &amp; are to this day ſo irreuerently plaid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as people of all profeſſions, fooles and phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions make vp their morning and euening meditations with the moſt vnciuill termes, which they may deuiſe againſt them. How ſottiſh would that Cobler haue beene accounted in theſe daies, who, being controlde by a Painter for preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to giue his iudgement of a Picture aboue the ſhooe, departed quietly, and would not once replie vpon <hi>Ne ſutor vltra crepidam? Tractant Fabrilia Fabri</hi> was the olde ſaying, euerie man was to attend that which belonged to his Trade, but the age is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in which S. <hi>Hierome</hi> liued, and of which he vſed this ſaying, <hi>Scribimus indocti docti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poemata paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>19.</hi> can. nulli fas.</note> The Ieſuites might haue plaid with their Canon vpon ſuch as reſiſted the Apoſtolicall Decrees, and without blame haue made a breach, yea and vtterly haue ruinated thoſe whom in ſuch cauſe they ſhould aſſault; but to diſturbe and infect the aire which hath giuen them life with this breath; Hearken ô ye facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ye are Rebels, ye are Schiſmatikes, ye are excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated perſons, Irregular, no better then Sooth-ſayers
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15701:3"/> and Idolators, and as Ethnickes and Publicans was neither commendable in ſuch as make ſhewe to immitate Ieſus, nor euer will be iuſtifiable againſt thoſe Prieſts, who at the ſight of the Breue gaue an inuincible argument of their obedience to Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall decrees, and haue a long time aduentured their liues for the dignitie of the Sea Apoſtolike as farre as the Ieſuites haue for anie matter whatſoeuer. Other who either immediately, or by others haue a depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Ieſuits, ſome for want of other inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome to keepe their tongues in vre, ſome to trie who can vtter the moſt deſpitefull ſpeeches againſt thoſe Prieſtes to whom perchaunce they haue beene moſt bounde, ſome to winne all to goe one way (which they may and do full euil) muſt follow their dam, and crow after kinde, leaſt their ſpirituall guides and grand-fathers ſhould abando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them as a misbegotten brood. And while they all euerie one at his Qu play their parts, as ſhrewd boyes, while they byte kick and ſcratch, crie that they cannot be let alone, they make a great ſhewe as though they would moſt gladly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a peace. F. <hi>Garnet</hi> the head of the Ieſuites here in England ſolliciteth ſome to be a meane for peace, but with ſuch condition, as no ſatisfaction be talked on for the clamorous ſpeeches before rehearſed, and what hath vpon them enſued to manie, who haue with the beſt deſerued of Gods Church and a freſh offer of ſome things moſt ſeriouſly promiſed at the firſt attonement, and not as yet performed. At the ſame time flie Letters like Bats, and are ſhewed in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret to ſuch as haue no liſt but to lie ſtill in a groſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15701:3"/> and affected ignorance, which manner of carriage what elſe could it portend other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a defect of truth, largeneſſe of conſcience, a freſh alarum to farther tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults? and if F. <hi>Garnet</hi> the Superiour of the Ieſuites were of counſel thervnto, ſmal is his ſinceritie (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer his charitie is) which hee pretendeth in his mock-offer of peace. The preſumption that he was of counſell to theſe Letters of M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> M. <hi>Blackwels</hi> inſtructions, where after a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of vnitie betweene the Prieſts and the Ieſuites, the Archprieſt is willed to ſeeke the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and counſell of the Superiour of the Ieſuites in the greater matters, <hi>Curabit Archipresbiter in rebus maioribus iudicium quoque eius conſiliumque acquirere;</hi> great follie it were to ſhut this Letter of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſts from his matters of great weight, being an anſwere to ſeditious Bookes (as hee termeth them) and ſuch as may bring great hurt to the Church of God, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently an endangering of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt to ſay that he did not take the aduice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Prouinciall of the Ieſuites herein (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Bookes concerning them as much as him) F. <hi>Liſter</hi> being alwayes readie with his Canon. <hi>Nulli fas eſt vel velle vel poſſe tranſgredi Apostolicae ſedis praecepta, <hi>It is not lawfull for any to be willing or able to tranſgreſſe the precepts of the Sea Apoſtolicke.</hi>
               </hi> With the which he, his fellow Ieſuites, and the Archprieſt alſo are perſwaded that the Prieſtes are ſhaken, yea &amp; brought to vtter ruine. Theſe Letters of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt while we ſhal take the paines to anſwere for the inſtruction of ſuch as either vpon their owne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15701:4"/> haue erred, or by the double diligence of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue bene miſled, and ſhewe how we are dealt withall by the one, while an offer of a mock-peace is tendered by the other, we craue no other then indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferencie in the Chriſtian Reader, and nothing doubt but to diſcouer the drift both of him who diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth not himſelfe or his intentions, and alſo of the other who to colour his owne and his fellowes miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours in this matter (as if hee were no partie, much leſſe the principall maintainer of this faction againſt vs) pretendeth to be a ſtickler betweene the Archprieſt and vs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all true hartie affection I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15701:4"/>
            <head>The Copie of M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> his Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My verie Reuerend, and verie louing Aſsistants.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO my great ſorrow, two Bookes haue bene ſet out, by our deare Brethren, whom all you loue in the bowels of Chriſt, and who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue ſought by all Fatherly meanes to winne and reduce to vnitie, great reaſon it had bin, that a thing propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Pope his holines, ſhould not with ſo great ſcandall of our cauſe, and ioy of our aduerſaries, haue firſt bene divulged to all ſortes of people, before it could poſſibly come to his ſight &amp; cenſure, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes neuer ment to be preſented to him, although meanes muſt be made by me, that it may come to his reading, and the view thereof will grieue him much, becauſe he loueth, and euery where deſireth peace.</p>
            <p>It cannot be liked of, that we ſhould write one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an other, and therefore no other anſwere ſhall be ſent now then this. And my deſire is, that all good Catholiques, according to their duties, do thinke well of their Superiours, and if they haue any doubt, do ſuſpend their iudgements vntil they heare the full deciding of the cauſe, for herein is touched the credit of all Superiours in the world.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15701:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The principall points they touch are theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The diuiſion at <hi>Wisbitch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 The ſedition of the Colledge at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the gouernment of their Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</item>
               <item>3 The inſtitution of our authoritie.</item>
               <item>4 The cenſuring them of ſchiſme.</item>
               <item>5 The vſage of the two Age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts they ſent to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 The decrees I made, and the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt point was a thing being ſince ended with great edification, and by the meanes principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of theſe, which are moſt condemned.</p>
            <p>It concerneth authoritie, it being more auncient, and hauing orders taken at the attonement by their owne conſent. It is well knowne at <hi>Rome</hi> by whoſe meanes they were diſanulled, neither was it more vnfitting for thoſe which liued in one houſe to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like rules for ſuch as voluntarily demaunded and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted them, then to procure a ſodalitie abroad.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond point concerneth the Superiours there, whoſe authoritie is moſt greeuouſly, and moſt daungerouſly contemned, who had the hearing of the cauſes, and by great reaſon ought to make orders for the Seminaries, which they that complaine ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer built.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The third point is cleare by his holines Breue,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15701:5"/> and no leſſe could be done, then to accept the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and to accept it when it came at the firſt. For I haue deſired to obey, and I ſignified then how vnfit I was to haue ſo great a charge, and am euer readie to depoſe it for the loue of God, and the profite of his Church, vpon the leaſt knowledge of my Superiours will and commaundement: for my delight is not ſo much in it, as theſe authours do affirme, neither was it publiſhed at any time with vntruthes nor by anie ſuch vnſeemly meanes, which might giue ſhewe of anie litle oſtentation.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The matter of Schiſme was according to my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion which now I retaine, yet with ſubmiſſion to holie Church, what I ſhewed them was done in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie for their better inſtruction and ſpeedie reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which alſo was ſent them by mee in ſecret, and therein no particular perſon was named, It was but an arbytrarie matter diſcuſſed among the learned which bringeth no loſſe of credite to either part, I gaue them all expreſſe libertie to thinke what they would heerein, for it is but a matter of opinion, and therefore not worthie to make a matter of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which part ſoeuer was true. I ſought by learned diſcourſes and cenſures not ſo much the forwardnes of my opinion as of their amendment. What I ſent them to view was in maner of a Fatherly admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not to ſtirre vp or to feede a further diſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Our endeuours were for peace, our allowance for our paines is their contentious and verie ſcandalous behauiours, for which they can haue no excuſe after three diuers Letters of the Protector our ſuperiour:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15701:6"/> and not Protector onely of the Colledge,<note place="margin">Nauar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. <hi>1.</hi> de offic. Iudic. deleg. Iacobus Stroozzeus ab vrc. de of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio vicar. Epi. qui dicit eſſe comu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> as they ſay, For before anie Seminary was, we had a Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of England, whoſe Letters Pattents according to the beſt Canoniſts, were to be credited &amp; were to be receiued verie obediently.</p>
            <p>An attonement was made by which I hoped all variance had bin appeaſed, what was ſaid afterwards or done by me, was done vpon their prouocation, for ceaſe they would not to write, to ſpeake, to exact ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and to publiſh vntruths of vs contrarie to the order which I had preſcribed, wherevpon I was enforced to write a large Latine admonition to one of them, and to an other an Engliſh Letter, to gaine a ſtaie of wronges, which were offered mee about the matter of ſchiſme.</p>
            <p n="5">5 For the vſage of the two Agents ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> concerneth the Pope &amp; the two Cardinalls, and the Fiſcall of the reformation ordeined by his holineſſe who were priuie to all, and as one of theſe Cardinals appointed Iudges not long ſince haue written, they were <hi>Interpretes voluntatis Papae, &amp; non ſolum iudices,</hi> If anie inferiour were culpable herein, meete it were to complaine priuately to our Superiours, and not with great ſcandall to offend all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p n="6">6 My decrees were neceſſarie, for they containe nothing but prohibition of things otherwiſe vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and partly alſo forbidden by Cardinall <hi>Caietane,</hi> and the euent ſheweth how neceſſary they were, and the cauſe of their paines inflicted <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſcandals and ſeditions could not be preuented, for heere I cannot well haue the vſe of <hi>forum conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſum,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15701:6"/> neither could I cite or produce witneſſes, nor conueniently meete with euerie one <hi>poſt factum,</hi> And ſurely my cenſures haue done good not to a fewe.</p>
            <p>As for the execution of them ſince the appeale, I proceed vpon other cauſes then vpon the appeale, which doth not (as they imagine) take away autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but only if it be of validitie, deuolueth the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their ſpecified to the Sea Apoſtolicke, If I require ſubmiſſion, an oath of obedience, of ſuch as haue ſpread abroad ſuch greeuous complaints againſt me, it is but a ſlender ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſuch iniuries and not more then all vſe now to do at their firſt miſſion, how much more where there was tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo much to be looked for.</p>
            <p>And here I am to warne all to conſider what hurt may come to the Church of God by theſe ſeditious bookes, and therefore deſire all to be dutifull in their cenſure, and carefull to hinder the divulging of ſuch bookes now being expected, and to be induſtrious in notefying vnto all the truth.</p>
            <p>The points co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined confute themſelues, though to my griefe they diſcouer ouermuch paſſion.</p>
            <p>And whereas diuers of theſe whoſe names were ſubſcribed to the appeale haue denied that euer they were priuie to it, and I doubt not the moſt part of the ſame neuer knew of any ſuch ſlaunderous writing, Theſe ſhall be to exhort them to ſignifie ſo much to my ſelfe or elſe by writing or in perſon to ſome of my Aſſiſtants, and they ſhall haue me moſt readie to giue them all manner of comfort, and ſo I deſire you to haue a great care to compoſe all theſe contentions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15701:7"/> and procure peace and by all faire meanes to recouer ſuch as by infirmitie haue erred. The times are daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and enemies are watchfull, many are ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, the increaſe of Catholicke Religion is hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, God is offended with theſe contentious procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and therefore let vs ſeeke after peace.</p>
            <p>Surely, happie we ſhall be &amp; bleſſed, for this our ſo godly a labour, bleſſed are the peace-makers, for they ſhall be called the ſonnes of God, to whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection I commend you all, humbly deſiring you to to pray for me, and ſo I take my leaue, this 23. of Iune. 1601.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. B. <hi>Archprieſt. Angl. Pronot. Apoſtolicus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15701:7"/>
            <p>IN theſe Letters of the Archprieſt are ſo many, and daungerous rockes againſt which not altogether ſenceleſſe people waſte themſelues, as it cannot be deemed a labor blame-worthie ſo to diſcouer them, as ſuch as will may perceiue them before their caſe become deſperate. Let his fatherlie loue, and care of his deare brethren (as he termeth vs) be meaſured by his carriage toward vs. For our maintaining of our ſelues not to be ſchiſmatikes (a matter of opinion not worthie (as here in his anſwere to the fourth point he confeſſeth) to make a matter of contention which part ſoeuer was true), how many hath he ſuſpended, bereaued of their faculties, yea and interdicted, for which he hath no colour to ſhew anie authoritie but thoſe words in the Cardinals firſt Letters <hi>Poſt debitas admonitiones ac reprehenſiones fraterna charitate praemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas liceat etiam paenis coercere Eccleſiaſticis, <hi>It ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for you after due admonition &amp; warning in brotherly chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to puniſh with Eccleſiaſticall penalties.</hi>
               </hi> Which ſentence is preſently limited by the words immediatly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Oblatione nimirum facultatum vel ſuſpenſione, <hi>By ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away faculties or ſuſpending?</hi>
               </hi> How many haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon bene diſturbed out of their places of reſidence? how many cleane abandoned of their friends? how many haue bene laid open to moſt wicked detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tongues? how many in daunger to periſh by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine hauing no other meanes to liue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of ſuch as to whom they do miniſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? and for what? for maintaining an opinion which were it true or falſe were no matter worthie to make contention as M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> here confeſſeth.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15701:8"/> 
               <hi>Quis ex vobis patrem petit pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quid lapidem dabit illi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. <hi>If any of you</hi>
               </hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>aſketh bread of his father, will he giue him a ſtone? Or if he aſke him for fiſh, in place of a fiſh will he giue him a ſerpent? Or if he ſhall aſke for an egge, will he reach him a ſcorpion?</hi> If no father would doo this, how dooth M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> ſay that hee hath ſought by all fatherly meanes to win and reduce vs to vnitie, hauing ſought by the aforeſaid meanes to driue vs to ſay againſt our owne ſoules that we were ſchiſmatikes, and to ſuffer others without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to lay it euery day in our teeth, for defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that which (as himſelfe here confeſſeth) was not worthy to make a matter of contention, which part ſoeuer was true?</p>
            <p>But to come to that which he thinketh great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that is, that a thing propounded to the Pope his holineſſe, ſhould not firſt haue bin divulged to all ſorts of people, before it could poſſibly come to his ſight, and cenſure. What if this were ſo litle againſt reaſon, as the contrary had bene great folly? for who knoweth not, that the Ieſuites do lie ſo in waight to intercept what paſſeth too and fro, that a ſmall Letter can hardly and that very ſeldome eſcape them? how then ſhould this booke by any ſecret co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyance ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer haue gone without danger of being at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions, before it could come to the Pope his viewe and cenſure? It might therefore with great reaſon haue bene at the firſt propounded to all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that thereby ſome one Copie or other might come to his holineſſe his view; and if this courſe had beene taken in the divulging of theſe bookes, what
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15701:8"/> reaſon hath M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> to ſay that perhaps it was neuer meant to be ſhewed to his holineſſe? Could the Prieſts be ſo fooliſh in M. <hi>Blackwells</hi> conceit, that they would make a diſcourſe of their miſeries with petition to be relieued by his holineſſe, dedicate the booke vnto him, and publiſh it in that maner, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer meane that it ſhould bee preſented vnto him? how could M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> frame his imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this, who could not but knowe long ſince, that of the 10. which were ſent ouer for <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome of his friendes tooke the tythe where it was not due? What if that booke which M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> or his friend ſeiſed on were the booke that was meant to haue bene preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Pope, who were they then that perhaps neuer meant the booke ſhould be preſented to him? But the other 9. being ſafely deliuered, as long ſince we vnderſtood from <hi>Paris</hi> whether they were ſent, perhaps his holineſſe hath had the view of one; and if M. <hi>Blackwel</hi> do know any thing to the contrary, we will yeeld him moſt heartie thankes to make the meanes to haue it come to his holineſſe his reading, for we doo aſſure him and all other who haue made doubt thereof, that it is our ſpeeciall deſire, as in time it will wel be ſeene, and the more griefe his holineſſe ſhall take thereat, the leſſe thankes will they haue who haue ſo long a time deluded him with falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations, and no doubt will prouide in ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort for a true and vnfeined peace to continue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs. And therefore feare we the leſſe that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may bee charged to giue any ſcandall to our friends, or ioy to our aduerſaries, no man beeing to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15701:9"/> be accounted a friend which ſhould take offence where no cauſe is giuen, or eſteemed our aduerſarie who would ioy at our good, or the furtherance of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny honeſt cauſe, how contrary ſoeuer he may bee to truth in ſome other kinde. <hi>Praeceptor vidimus quenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in nomine tuo eijcientem daemonia, &amp;c. <hi>Maiſter</hi>
               </hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to our Sauiour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.</note>) <hi>we ſawe one caſt out diuels in thy name and we forbid him it becauſe he is not of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and Ieſus ſaid vnto him, doo not forbid him, for he who is not againſt you is with you.</hi> Shall we then call them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, who ſhall reioyce at their reliefe, who are vniuſtly oppreſſed, and not rather pray <hi>vt iuſtificentur adhuc</hi> and thinke our ſelues much bound vnto them, whoſoeuer they be who ſhall fauour or further vs in our iuſt cauſe? It cannot be liked of (ſaith M. <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>) that we ſhould write one againſt an other. How ſhall wee conſter this? was not and vnto this day is not the Ieſuits libell againſt the Prieſts liked, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Prieſts are called Rebells, Schiſmatikes, fallen from the Church and ſpouſe of Chriſt, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, irregular, infamous, diſobedient to Chriſt and his Vicar, factious, nothing better then ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, and Idollaters, as Ethnicks and Publicans? Dooth not M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> in his anſwere to the fourth point heere write abroad that he retaineth his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtill that we were ſchiſmatikes, and commendeth this rayling Libell of the Ieſuits for a learned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and cenſure? And can the purging of vs Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Prieſts from theſe wicked defamations (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound therevnto both for the defence of our good names, which vnleſſe we will be accounted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15701:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> cruell to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, we cannot let lie bleeding to the death, &amp; for their comfort whoſe ſoules haue a long time bin vnder our charge) be diſliked by any honeſt man? Is it to be thought that Gods cauſe can ſuffer diſhonour in any courſe, which is neceſſarie for the recouery of his Prieſts their honour, and doth he not well deſerue to be robbed of all that he hath, yea and baſted vntill all his bones do rattell in his skinne who vpon enuie that an aduerſary ſhould ioy, would omit a neceſſarie defence for his own reliefe? would there not be as many houters as hearers of one perſwading an other rather to let a third take away all his landes and goods then bring it to a publike triall vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of a thing not to be liked that one ſhould plead openly againſt an other? would theeues deſire to meete with better copeſmates when they would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelues, or refuſe a triall where ſuch Iudges ſhould ſit vpon the bench? It falleth out many times that with leſſe daunger a man may take a Beare by the tooth then awake a ſleeping dogge. Had not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes bene before in vaine attempted for the remedie of what we haue felt, or were not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent extremities ouer great into whiche wee are brought by the trump of euerie looſe tongue where before they were poſſeſſed with this ſpirite butter would not haue melted, we might haue bin blamed for our publiſhing in this ſort &amp; laying open thereby to the whole worlde who they are that diſturbe the peace, which ought to haue bene mainteined amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs. And if any doubt hereof ſhal grow in any, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is, as alſo M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> deſireth, that all do thinke
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15701:10"/> well of their ſuperiors, and ſuſpend their iudgements vntil they heare the ful deciding of the cauſe, which, howſoeuer the deſire of ſome be therein ſatisfied, is not to withdrawe their charitie from the reliefe of Prieſts who want, for this is not to ſuſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but their charitie, and not only to iudge but to puniſh alſo, much leſſe do they ſuſpend their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments who turne Prieſts out of their houſen, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime day and night againſt them, ſhut them from the ſeruice of God, and diuide themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them and their Catholike friends in praier and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Sacraments vpon an opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which was not worthie to make a matter of contention, which part were true as M. <hi>Blackwel</hi> affirmeth in his anſwere here to the fourth point. I wiſh the ignorance were ſuch as it might excuſe, but I feare it is too much affected, where vnder pretence of <hi>obedience</hi> it muſt not be ſeen where ſuperiors haue not done ſo well as they might haue done, and how thoſe who are condemned ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally as diſobedient &amp; factious againſt their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours haue behaued themſelues in all dutifull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to all ſuperiors, which they knew, and how farre they were bounde to ſhewe obedience. And if the Prieſts haue bene compelled to this hard choyce as either they muſt ſuſtaine infinite iniuries, and oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, or redeeme themſelues in this ſort from ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued an oppreſſion, no ſuperiour in the world can iuſtly finde himſelfe touched in credit, but ſuch whom the Apoſtle calleth <hi>Principes &amp; poteſtates mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di rectores tenebrarum harum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>M. Archprieſt gathereth ſixe principall points
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15701:10"/> which he ſaith are touched, and maketh anſwere to euery one in order as he putteth them downe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>The firſt is the diuiſion at <hi>Wisbich,</hi> to which hee ſaith that it was long ſince ended with great aedifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by the meanes principally of thoſe, which are moſt condemned. But he doth neither name the parties, nor giue to vnderſtand who they are which condemne them. He vſed ſilence perchaunce in this, becauſe he muſt haue named either thoſe whom he would not, or thoſe whom he ſhould not; for it is ſo well knowne as none without great want of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie can deny that M. <hi>Iohn Muſh</hi> and M. <hi>Richard Dudly</hi> two Prieſts now condemned by the Archprieſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites and their adherents came out of the North to their great paines, and charge to <hi>Wisbich,</hi> and from thence to <hi>London,</hi> where after that they had bene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mocked by the head of the Ieſuites, at the laſt with maruellous importunitie wroong from him certaine Letters to his fellow Ieſuites at <hi>Wisbich,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſight whereof there was a peace made, ſuch as it was, it might haue bene much better, and ſpeedier (as by this it ſeemeth) if it had before ſo pleaſed the head of the Ieſuites to haue enterpoſed himſelfe as charitie would he ſhould haue done, the head of the Faction at <hi>Wisbich</hi> being at his commaund, and one who rather then ſo great a ſcandall ſhould haue riſen for his cauſe ſhould haue ſuffered himſelfe to haue bin caſt ouer the Caſtle wall, which in thoſe tumults hee affirmed ſome would doo rather then the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his preferment ouer all the ſecular Prieſts there and fellow priſoners ſhould not goe forward. At an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15701:11"/> other time M. <hi>Alb. Dolman</hi> ſhould haue made peace, but the Ieſuite who ſhould haue bene the Superiour there vnder the tytle of an Agent vnderſtanding of ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which he liked not, a litle before that all ſhould haue bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded found the meanes to rid him away. And I do verily thinke that there are fewe who thinke, and none who know that the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is as yet ended, which is no great aedificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, God pardon them who are the cauſe thereof. And moſt vnworthily are thoſe ſcandalous proceedings at <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bich</hi> compared with the ſodalitie which was to be procured abroad. For the firſt foundation of them vvere detractious, &amp; infamous ſpeeches againſt ſuch as in all times among Chriſtians haue bene had in great reuerence, &amp; their faults (if they had any) vvere concealed, not publiſhed abroad to the vvorld, much leſſe vvas it liked that any ſhould be falſly obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, for no ſuch courſe vvas iudged in thoſe dayes to ſtand vvith the glory of God. The drift of thoſe proceedings vvas to make a Ieſuite Superiour ouer the ſecular Prieſts, or to maintaine that ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diuiſion which hath euen to this day followed theron, vpon ſome other ground doubtleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which their fauourites doo moſt ſeriouſly vrge, to wit that ſome of that ſocietie haue bene the maiſters or trainers vp of ſome of the ſecular Prieſts beyond the ſeas, for by this argument euery one whoſoeuer is no Schoolemaiſter or trayner vp of youth, yea all Princes muſt yeeld themſelues to be vnder the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not only of thoſe who were ſometime their Schoolemaiſters, but of euery pettie Schoolemaiſter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15701:11"/> becauſe once they haue bene trained vp by ſome of that profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and ſuch as haue much greater know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; facility in teaching or training muſt humble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to euery Punie becauſe they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues had once maiſters of that profeſſion of which this Punie is: &amp; perchance no leſſe abſurditie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this was that in <hi>Wisbich,</hi> when many graue, wiſe, and learned men were to become ſubiect to a Ieſuite, becauſe forſooth (as theſe fauourites of the Ieſuits alledge) the Ieſuits haue the bringing vp of ſome Prieſts beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſeas. The ſodalitie which was to be procured abroad was for ſuch as voluntarily would ioyne themſelues to liue vnder rules, and ſuperiors to be choſen by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the priuitie of his holineſſe, and without any ſchiſme or faction againſt thoſe who would not be of the Sodalitie. So that the difference was very great betweene the humour of the Ieſuites in that diuiſion at <hi>Wisbich,</hi> and the peaceable endeuours of the Prieſts abroad, to which the Ieſuites hauing no very good liking, laboured to effect what before they had miſſed with a peece of more cunning, and by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter meanes procured a ſuperiour ouer the Prieſts, who vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peril of being euery day to be put downe, muſt like whatſoeuer they ſhould lay before him, and in the mean while they muſt be of his priuy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in matters of greateſt waight, and allow of none but ſuch as are devoted vnto them for his ordinarie aſſiſtants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>The ſecond poynt concerneth the ſuperiours there, whoſe authoritie (he ſaith) is moſt grieuouſly, and moſt dangerouſly contemned: hee might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15701:12"/> be accounted wiſe who ſhould diuine a right that which is meant hereby. There haue beene as many viſitations on the behalfe of the Students, as of the Ieſuites; and as for the ſuperiours, I haue ſeene a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fa. <hi>Parſons</hi> own penning, dated the 5. of April 1599. wherein he ſaith that perhaps ſome one mans actions in the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Colledge at <hi>Rome,</hi> in ſome certaine points were not ſo much to Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Allane</hi> his liking, and without perhaps the orders, which were miſliked, were by F. <hi>Par.</hi> contrary to his owne promiſe brought into the Seminary of <hi>Rome;</hi> where indeed there are new buildings but they were not at the charge of the Ieſuites, but of the Colledge, and if it be richer in cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, it is poorer in vineyards, and in this new building there are very few more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> halfe ſo manie ſtudents as were before the new buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings were erected, and theſe fewe are ſo ſtraungely diuided, and debarred each others comfort, as how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Ieſuites gaine therby, or ioy therat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the ſtudents may iuſtly ſay vnto them for all this great boaſt of buildings, <hi>Nec multiplicaſtis gentem nec magnificaſtis laetitiam.</hi> That Colledge was firſt an Hoſpitall founded by our Princes for the reliefe of ſuch as went on pilgrimage to thoſe holie places, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it was endewed with an Abbacie by Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> of happie memorie the 13. of that name, and Doctor <hi>Lewis</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caſſana</hi> bore the name to be the erector of it as a Colledge, as Cardinal <hi>Allane</hi> did of the Colledge at <hi>Rhemes</hi> now tranſlated to <hi>Doway:</hi> and no diſpraiſe to anie, thoſe two Seminaries and their founders were thoſe who brought England to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15701:12"/> that paſſe, that as wel the Laitie as the Cleargie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were admired throughout all Chriſtendome for their fortitude in Gods cauſe and faithfulneſſe in all their temporall affaires. And it is well knowne that theſe two were of thoſe who complained. The one at the verie firſt beginning as one well acquainted with the Ieſuites courſes, and had ſerued that mirror of pietie and wiſedome Cardinall <hi>Boromeo</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Millane,</hi> who diſcharged them of the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Seminaries. The other ſomewhat with the lateſt, but yet in ſuch ſort as Doctor <hi>Haddock</hi> who pretendeth that he was the Cardinals Nephew mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſpirit after the Cardinalls death writ vnto a worſhipfull Knight in <hi>Spaine</hi> theſe words to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, <hi>Profecto bene mortuus eſt ſi enim vixiſſet &amp; ſibi &amp; patriae ſuae maximu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dedecus peperiſſet. <hi>He is dead in a good time, for if he had liued he had moſt greatly diſhonoured himſelfe and his Country.</hi>
                  </hi> And why maſt. Doctor? for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth he was carried away againſt the Ieſuites by his Nephew M. <hi>Hesket,</hi> M. <hi>Throckmorton,</hi> M. <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> &amp; all the Gentlemen of our nation who were then at <hi>Rome,</hi> but eſpecially by my Lord of <hi>Caſſana</hi> through whoſe meanes M. Doctor <hi>Haddock</hi> was diſcarded, as one that was factious againſt the ſtudents in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Ieſuites, and loſt thereby as he ſaid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Nephewes part, which he had bene promiſed often by the Cardinall and he moſt certainly expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Seminaries in <hi>Spaine</hi> haue bene builded by the Ieſuites meanes with no ſmall ſummes of mony, which perchance would haue bene much better and with far more merit imployed in the reliefe of poore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15701:13"/> afflicted Catholikes as well of the Laitie, as the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, who liued in exile, either in Colledges, which for want were many times in ieopardie to haue bene diſſolued, or elſewhere abroad and famiſhed, but the yce was broken, and the way made by ſecular Prieſts before any Ieſuites attempted it, as in all honeſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters it fareth, &amp; F. <hi>Parſons</hi> entered into their worke, and brought it indeed to this paſſe at which now it is by making the ſtudents do that of which ſince they repent themſelues and he hath no great cauſe to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in, as the ſubſcribing to the title of the Infant, and what elſe hee would, hauing gotten their names to three ſeuerall blankes. But theſe Prieſts, who were in this ſort the founders of the Seminaries in <hi>Spaine,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not the ſtorers for lyme and ſtone, were kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen very well to haue bene of thoſe who did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they liued, and the ſuruiuer is to this day one of them who do complaine. Neither is this to diſcouer more then needeth (although no doubt it be more then the Ieſuites and their fauourites would haue talked abroad the matter is ſo honeſt) for what Letters are written, and publiſhed by them in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wherein themſelues and their aſſociates to winne Engliſh Catholickes inſert not their building of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, which the Catholickes might haue built with more eaſe &amp; leſſe charge, if they conſider what they are put to by reaſon of thoſe plots, by which the Seminaries haue bene built, and the often attempts made againſt our Countrey vpon the fooliſh hopes, which ſome haue had vpon thoſe plots? ſome like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take exceptions that theſe matters are touched
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15701:13"/> ſomewhat in the cenſure vpon F. <hi>Parſons</hi> Letter, but they conſider not that F. <hi>Parſons</hi> draue vs to it by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our charge, that we were not ſo much hated of the Councell of England as the Ieſuites, and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt. His guiltie conſcience gaue him what he and his aſſociates had deſerued, although he thought it pollicie to conceale the cauſe thereof, and to leaue ſuch an obloquie (as it could not be taken for other) to euery man to ſcan theron, and to ſeeke ſome cauſe for that, which if they would they might ſee daily was voyd of all truth, the greateſt part without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thoſe who ſuffered hauing beene ſuch as were not of the faction of the Ieſuites, and ſhall we be blamed if we ſolue thoſe aenigmes which F. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and his fellowes needleſly propoſe againſt vs, and leaue to the worſt ſence which may be made of them?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>The third point he ſaith is cleare by his holineſſe Breue. Who calleth this in queſtion? or how doth this prooue that no leſſe could be done the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to accept the authoritie, and to accept it when it came at the firſt, which was a whole year before the Breue came, and without not only a confirmation from his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but alſo without ſufficient teſtimony to binde vs to accept thereof being to ſo great a preiudice to many, in which caſe a Cardinals teſtimony doth not binde any to beleeue that which is affirmed by him, much leſſe if it euidently containe falſhood, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe nothing elſe but falſhood for the foundation? But neither was it ſo cleare perchance as he thinketh, for a Breue may come from diuers places, and be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15701:14"/> an Apoſtolicall Breue, and his holineſſe no w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t acquainted therewith, and there was no ſmall cauſe to ſuſpect ſo much of this, not only for that it was a confirmation of a thing done vpon ſo falſe a ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (to wit a diuiſion betweene the Seminary Prieſts in England and the Catholickes) as the contrary might very eaſily haue bene knowne if any but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt men had bene asked the queſtion, but alſo for that it is a confirmation of certaine Letters Patents which we neuer ſawe, although the Archprieſt hath ſhewed two ſeuerall Letters (if our memories faile vs not) of the inſtitution of his authoritie. For this Breue is a confirmation of certaine Letters Patents by which M. <hi>George Blackwell</hi> is deputed by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Caietane</hi> an Archprieſt of Engliſh Catholikes, for the better gouernment and vnion of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> and thoſe Letters which M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> did obey ſo readily did onely depute him Arch-prieſt of the Seminary Prieſts which are or ſhall be in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> for remedy of a diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuggeſted to be between the Seminary Prieſts &amp; Catholikes in <hi>England,</hi> wherein who will may perceiue a very great difference. But to returne to M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> his acknowledging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf how vnfit he was to haue ſo great a charge, or his readineſſe to depoſe it for the loue of God, no man is to enter into his inward motions, but doubtleſſe he did not long after taunt thoſe Prieſtes, who were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the procuring of the ſodallitie, of which wee ſpake before, and in a triumphing maner writ abroad that theyr endeuours were by this his authoritie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15701:14"/> brought to ruine. We could alſo prooue that thoſe Letters of the Cardinals were not warme in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds before hee thought vpon the vſe of his authoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome in particular: yea &amp; other who were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be of his priuie councell letted not to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at that time that there were ſuch courſes to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt ſome, that they doubted whether they would continue Catholique. M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> addeth here alſo that his authoritie was not publiſhed at any time with vntruths. In the Bookes printed, and ſent abroad, it is ſaid that he did not only publiſh his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie with vntruthes, but being taken in the maner confeſſed as much, and that M. <hi>Collington</hi> and M. <hi>Charnocke</hi> are readie to iuſtifie it before God, and the world vpon their oaths. And if they were both dead his owne Letters of the 2. of March following will proue it euidently enough, in which he hath theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Laſtly you quarrell againſt the Archpreſbyter, and gladly you would bruſe his credit vpon the roaring noyſe of an angrie man, clouded in his vnderſtanding, if not cloyed about his hart with two many fumes of ambition. Vpon his detractiue infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you publiſh that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Archpreſbyter ſhould report that he had authoritie to excommunicate &amp; to commaund to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which now vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better ſcanning his authoritie he goes from. Againe ſhewing his inſtructions ſaid they were made at <hi>Rome,</hi> and by the contents being conuinced they were made in <hi>England,</hi> could not denie it. Sir, the Archpreſbyter hath to doo about excommunications, and the ſending to the court of <hi>Rome:</hi> for by his Commiſſion he is charged to ſpecifie all ſuche rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and contumacies as are too familiar with you, if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuppreſſed with his authoritie at home, and to intimate the ſame to the Lord Protector his grace, and ſo by his meanes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15701:15"/> to procure excommunication or the ſending for to <hi>Rome</hi> for the redreſſe of ſuch licentiouſneſſe. And for the particular inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he neuer ſaid they were all made at <hi>Rome,</hi> but that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions made at <hi>Rome</hi> gaue him authoritie to ſet downe rules about all particular matters, and caſes of ſuch qualitie. And ſo thoſe inſtructions which troubled the eares of your ſurly, and froward Father, may be ſaide in reſpect of their authoritie to haue proceeded from <hi>Rome.</hi> And thus the Archpreſbyter whoſe name you put downe in plaine Letters, that euery bodie might view how you haue graced him, <hi>Ipſe liberatus eſt a laqueo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantium &amp; a verbo aſpero,</hi> he hath auoyded your ſnare, and the ſharpneſſe of your ſlaunderous ſpéech. The iniquitie of proud perſons hath bene multiplied ouer him, but he hoping in our Lord hath not bene weakened.</q> Thus farre M. <hi>Blackwell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How many orders hath M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> taken at <hi>Rome,</hi> when he hath taken ſeuen by authoritie from <hi>Rome?</hi> Some inſtructions are confeſſed to haue bene ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which were not made at <hi>Rome</hi> any otherwiſe then M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> may be ſaid to haue bene made Prieſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſe what were thoſe which troubled the eares of the ſurly, and froward Father, and were then abſolutely propoſed among others as inſtructions annexed to his Commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſo palpably inſerted, as he confeſſed that they were of his owne, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he pretended to ſhew ſuch as the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſpake of to be annexed vnto it? at that time this ſhift was not deuiſed, that he had authoritie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Rome</hi> to make rules, and therefore might propoſe what he would, and ſay it was made at <hi>Rome.</hi> But the <hi>plaudite</hi> in the end with a Pſalme might haue bene vſed vpon ſome greater victorie then this poore ſhift was, that inſtructions might be ſaid to haue bin made at <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15701:15"/> becauſe they might be ſaid to haue bin made by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie which came from <hi>Rome,</hi> and that the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt could excommunicate, becauſe he could write to thoſe who could. But to ſay the truth what but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth is to be expected in the maintenance of that, which was begotten, bred, brought forth and nurſed with vntruth? M. <hi>Iames Standiſh</hi> a ſecular Prieſt in ſhewe, a Ieſuit by promiſe, went as a ſecular Prieſt in the name of the ſecular Prieſts who neuer ſent him, and dealt with his holines in this matter, fayning the conſent of the ſecular Prieſts thereto, which after his returne in the hearing of diuers Prieſtes, he ſaid was but an interpretatiue conſent, and that he preſumed that they would giue their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent. The matter being thus broached, as falſe a ſuggeſtion was made for the furtherance thereof, to wit, a dangerous and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diuiſion in Englande among the Seminarie Prieſts and Catholickes (as it is euidently to be ſeene in the Cardinall <hi>Caietanes</hi> Letters to M. <hi>Blackwell</hi>). The maner how it was propoſed, is in ſome part ſhewed before, and the poore ſhifts which were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward made to ſalue the vntruthes then vſed. What falſe aduiſoes were ſent into England by Fa. <hi>Parſons</hi> and M. <hi>Mar. Array</hi> about the handling thereof at <hi>Rome</hi> are diſcouered in the Engliſh booke; to which one more may bee added to ſhewe how in all places the ſureſt Anker of theſe proceedings hath beene falſhood. Fa. <hi>William Baldwin</hi> among other aduiſoes which hee ſent from <hi>Flaunders</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> 25. Februa. 1599. writ to his friend that the two Prieſts firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted that there might bee no ſubordination. A
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15701:16"/> pretie conceit when all their Letters which they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with them to his holineſſe demaunded a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. Secondly, that if needs there muſt bee a ſubordination, then ſome one which fauoured them might be created Biſhop; for which they named D. <hi>Gifford, Bagſhaw, Collington,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop.</hi> Is it likely that M. <hi>Biſhop</hi> would name himſelfe to bee made a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop? Fa. <hi>Parſons</hi> laboured M. <hi>Charnock</hi> to name ſome of theſe or ſome other which might haue fitted ſuch a turne, but bicauſe he could not obtaine of him to name any of theſe before he ſhould ſee the names of M. D. <hi>Barret</hi> and M. Doctor <hi>Ely,</hi> he cauſed M. D. <hi>Barrets</hi> name to be blotted out againe which was written in hope, and would not ſuffer M. D. <hi>Ely</hi> his name to be written, nor any thing elſe concerning that interrogatorie: which manner of carriage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with F. <hi>Baldwins</hi> Letter diſcouereth a good wil that F. <hi>Baldwin</hi> ſhould haue written the truth in this point. Thirdly he affirmeth in the ſame Letters that the two Prieſtes ſhould ſay that experience would teach if they had not their requeſt <hi>Quod indignabitur libertas ſi prematur</hi> theſe were their wordes ſaieth F. <hi>Baldwin.</hi> Can any man thinke that they would ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get themſelues as to threaten the Pope to his teeth, if hee would not graunt them what they would haue? but if F. <hi>Bald.</hi> writ doubtleſſe as he was enformed by Fa. <hi>Parſons,</hi> the greater is the confirmation of that which here we intend to ſhewe, that is how it hath from time to time bene lulled a ſleepe with falſhood, and therefore that the leſſe this wonder is now that it is auouched by M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> neuer to haue bene propoſed with vntruthes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15701:16"/>
               <head>4.</head>
               <p>The 4. point is touching the matter of ſchiſme which he ſaith was according to his opinion, which euen now he doth retaine. The head of the Ieſuites ſendeth abroad his Letters, by which hee ſignifieth that he would not be aſhamed to humble himſelfe to worke a peace, can it be thought that he was not pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to theſe Letters of the Archprieſt, whoſe counſell the Arch-prieſt in his inſtructions is willed to vſe in matters of weight? or can M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> forget that ſuch an aſſertion of F. <hi>Robert Iones</hi> the Ieſuite (being maintained by him) made a breach of the generall attonement which was made at the comming of the Breue? and muſt he needs euen while he exhorteth to peace declare now that ſuch is his opinion, as void of all learning as it hath bene &amp; is farre from all cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and publiſh his want of both in the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Is ſchiſme ſo ſmall a ſinne, as it is not worthie to make a matter of contention whether there were ſchiſme or no? or were ſchiſme ſo ſmall a matter as here it is made, is it charitie for M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> to publiſh his opinion in this ſort, knowing that the ſpeech of ſuch an opinion hath diuided men and their wiues, father and children, brothers and ſiſters, and the deareſt friendes, and hath bene the cauſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion among Prieſtes, and infinite ſinnes (if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction haue not loſt the nature of a ſinne) in all ſorts of people, to the perpetuall infamy as much as lyeth in them of Catholike Prieſtes, who perchance haue deſerued much better of Gods Church then they who haue maintained ſo long the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſchiſme againſt them? Can M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> expect any other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15701:17"/> thing of the Prieſts againſt whom hee ſtill declareth his opinion concerning this ſuppoſed ſchiſme, then to write, ſpeake, and exact ſatisfaction, hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo many iniuries by the like, and daily expect more? But now hee ſalueth all in ſaying, <hi>It was but an Arbitrarie matter diſcuſſed among the learned, which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth no loſſe of credit to ether part. I gaue them all expreſſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to thinke what they would herein, for it is but a matter of opinion, and therefore not worthy to make a matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention which part ſoeuer was true.</hi> Is it poſſible that M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> can ſay that he gaue all expreſſe libertie to thinke what they would as in an indifferent matter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aprill.</hi> 1599.</note> who in ſome of his Letters calleth it a ſoare, for the which F. <hi>Liſters</hi> Treatiſe of ſchiſme was ſuch a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,<note place="margin">14. <hi>March.</hi> 1600.</note> as it muſt not be called in, vntill this ſore were healed; In other Letters, that our condemned deſerts drew theſe names vpon vs, <hi>Factious, Schiſmatikes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated perſons, Irregular, as Ethnikes and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanes, and nothing better then Southſayers and Idollaters.</hi> Why did he publiſh that he had receiued a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the mother Cittie, that the refuſers of the appointed authoritie were ſchiſmatikes, and that hee would not giue abſolution to any who ſhould make no conſcience thereof, and gaue direction that they ſhould make account thereof, and before they receiued the benefit of abſolution make ſatisfaction, the manner whereof hee left to the diſcretion of a ghoſtly Fa. not touched with the note of ſchiſme? Is this to giue expreſſe libertie to all to thinke what they would herein?<note place="margin">21. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1600.</note> Did he not alſo ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his minde in other his Letters, where he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15701:17"/> his determination that hereafter whoſoeuer had faculties of him ſhould firſt be content to recall his peeuiſh opinion? did he not practiſe ſuch authoritie vpon M. <hi>Benſon</hi> when he would not giue him any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties vnleſſe hee would renounce the ſchiſmaticall conuenticle? he declared alſo that M. <hi>Tho. Moore</hi> had written in preiudice of the Faith, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he writ in our behalfe concerning this matter of Schiſme, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon neither his ordinary ghoſtly father would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacraments vnto him, nor his ghoſtly children receiue any of him, or be preſent when hee celebrated.<note place="margin">29. <hi>May.</hi> 1600.</note> Are not all Eccleſiaſticall perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vnder paine of ſuſpenſion, and loſſe of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties preſently to be incurred, and the Laitie vnder paine of being in the ſame ſort interdicted, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly nor indirectly by word or writing they maintaine the cenſure of <hi>Paris,</hi> although it were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon true informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe it cleared vs from ſchiſme and ſinne? and can it now be iuſtified, that hee gaue expreſſe libertie to all to thinke what they would, as of a matter which was not worthie to make a matter of contention which part ſoeuer was true?</p>
               <p>How often heretofore hath he commended that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of F. <hi>Liſter</hi> the Ieſuite, and euen now calleth it a learned diſcourſe &amp; cenſure, as if the dearth of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſcourſes continued ſtill? and for what is it ſo highly commended? for that it prooueth a matter which were it true were it otherwiſe, was not worthy to make any contention, and proueth it very ſimply God wot, in that only hee heapeth infamous names
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15701:18"/> out of his charitie vpon thoſe againſt whom it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. Yet leaaſt that the diſcourſe ſhould be called learned without cauſe a principall reaſon is here tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, that the authoritie was confirmed with three Letters of a Cardinall, and not only a Cardinall but a Protector, and not only a Protector of a Colledge, but a Protector of <hi>England.</hi> Let vs graunt that we ſaw three Letters of ſuch a Cardinall, although in verie deed there were but two ſhewed vnto vs (vnleſſe the altering of the firſt be accounted for one) &amp; the one of thoſe two was to this ende that the Arch-prieſt ſhould informe of the manners &amp; behauiours of the troubleſome (ſo it pleaſed his grace to terme thoſe who did not take his Letters for an Oracle, and yeeld themſelues before they had ſent to his holineſſe to vnderſtand his pleaſure in a matter thruſt vpon them vpon moſt wicked &amp; falſe ſuggeſtions, and with more authoritie in ſome ſort then euer any creature had, as vnder a colour of the greater glory of God, to dc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barre or throw a Prieſt out of his place, where in time of perſecution hee had ſome morall ſecuritie for his ſafetie, as well in reſpect of a conuenient ſhelter, as for neceſſary maintenance, hauing no liuings of the Church to ſupply his wants) Let vs I ſay graunt that we ſaw three, let vs ſay 30, and ſtand to the iudgment of learned men,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in cap. ſicut de ſent. excom. Felinus in ca. ad eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ibidem.</note> the cauſe is ours, that is to ſay, we were not bound to giue credit to ſo exorbitant a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo preiudiciall to many well deſeruing of Gods Church, vpon the teſtimony of a Cardinall, who alſo ſaying no otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he had a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement from his holineſſe to imploy himſelfe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15701:18"/> to make a peace betweene the Seminary Prieſts and the Catholickes (moſt iniuriouſly belyed at <hi>Rome</hi> to haue bene at variance)<note place="margin">Pan. in cap. quod ſuper fide inſtr. &amp; in cap. cum a nobis de teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; atteſt. Zecchius de ſtatu Ill. D. Car. num. <hi>9.</hi> Sil. verb. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus § <hi>15.</hi> &amp; verb. Teſtis § <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> and that it was the Popes will that there ſhould be a ſubornation for certaine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him by the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> (which were neuer as yet knowne what they were) made all the reſt, either of himſelfe, ignorant of Engliſh matters, or by the ſuggeſtion of the Ieſuites, betweene whom and the Prieſts were all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies which were in <hi>England.</hi> Neither doth it make any thing to the purpoſe, to alledge here that the Cardinall was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of <hi>England,</hi> for this act of his was a ſubdelega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as appeareth by the words of his Letter,<note place="margin">Angel. verb. Teſtis § <hi>14.</hi> Armill. ibid. § <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Te deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus cui vices noſtras pro tempore delegemus. <hi>We make choyce of you whom for the time we ſubdeligate in that charge which was committed to vs,</hi>
                  </hi> which was to make a peace betweene the Seminary Prieſts and the Catholickes who were ſaid to be fallen out, and not an act of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectorſhip: ſo that if it had bene knowne heere in England that he was Protector of England, yet it is as impertinently vrged in this place as the place out of <hi>Nauarre</hi> for the credite of a Protectors Letters, wherein no mention is made either of any Protector or any Letters, he ſpeaketh there of a farre different Officer which is called <hi>Conſeruator,</hi> whoſe office is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſet downe, <hi>Cap. fin. de officio &amp; pot. Iudi. deleg. in ſexto,</hi> then M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> vſeth his, and if <hi>Iacob Strozz.</hi> make no more to this purpoſe then <hi>Nauarre,</hi> theſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations might haue bene kept for ſome other places: very probable it is that this <hi>Iacob Strozz.</hi> doth handle ſomewhat of a Conſeruator as other Canoniſts do,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15701:19"/> and perchance nothing more of Protectors the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do. The office of a Protector ſtretcheth not it ſelf far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as may be gathered out of thoſe words of the Breue, <hi>Nationis Anglicanae apud nos &amp; Apostolicam ſedem Protector, <hi>Protector of the Engliſhe Nation heere with vs,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Clement. ſi ſummus pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifer. de ſent excom. ſuſp. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>and with the Sea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke,</hi> and this phraſe in the Breue doth not make him Protector of the Engliſh Nation, if before hee were not. But put the caſe in the beſt manner, and with the moſt aduantage. We did no otherwiſe then we might haue done if the Letters had come from his holineſſe,<note place="margin">Cap. ſi quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. de reſcrip. gloſi ibid. cap. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teneamur de praebend. gloſ. ibidem.</note> for we made no demur but with minde to giue a reaſonable cauſe thereof, which is lawfull for any man to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>The fift point concerneth the vſage of the two Agents at <hi>Rome,</hi> which if it hath bene ſhewed to be not as of Agents but as of patients, as being caſt into priſon before they were ſuffered to doo the parts of Agenrs, examined, afterward accuſed, not heard whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they deſired the copie of their accuſation to make anſwere therevnto, at which time only they were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to ſhewe their readineſſe to doo their duties, and after 14. weekes cloſe impriſonment bidden to conſult of their matters for which they came to <hi>Rome,</hi> (three dayes after that the Breue was gotten in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the authoritie) and notwithſtanding they put off their Caps to this Breue, and ſent it into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land that all might doo the like, they were baniſhed out of their Countrey, and confined without any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance for their neceſſary maintenance, being men who had ſpent all their life for and in the ſeruice of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15701:19"/> Gods Church. If this I ſay haue bene ſhewed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any blame laid upon the Pope Cardinalls or Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call of reformation, M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> ſhould not now to ſaue the credit of his particular Patrons, with ſcandal inſinuate that the Pope deſerued blame, for it hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies bene vndoubted that the Pope was misinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and therevpon did what he did, the Cardinall <hi>Caietane</hi> led altogether by the Ieſuites, the other not to contradict <hi>Caietane,</hi> the Fiſcall at <hi>Caietans</hi> deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and no part of any diſcourſe made heereof, can warrant M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> to ſay that either Pope, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardinals or Fiſcall were priuy to all, for the Pope ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard them; the Cardinalls but in anſwere for themſelues when they were brought before them to be accuſed by a couple of Proctors appointed for the Arch-prieſt, who after they ſawe the two Prieſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute vpon the point to anſwere their Libell or Bill of accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, obtained of the Cardinals that it might not be deliuered vnto them, ſo that heereby it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent alſo that the Cardinals were not priuie to all, the Fiſcall might heare or ſee their examinations or part thereof, which are not to be taken as relations of all which they could ſay, the Interrogatories beeing made at the diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of F. <hi>Parſons,</hi> and their anſwers cut off ſometime as being too lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſometime as more fit for other Interrogatories pretended to be made afterward. Who then with any reaſon can ſay that theſe were priuie to all? and if furthermore the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls were nothing but Interpreters of the Popes will, may not the truth be knowne without the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of all Chriſtendom, it being a thing very poſſible
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15701:20"/> that the Pope may be misinformed, &amp; do that which afterward he may wiſh vndone?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>6.</head>
               <p>The ſixt point is concerning his decrees, which as he ſaith <hi>were neceſſarie, for they containe nothing but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of things, otherwiſe vnlawfull, and partly alſo forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by Cardinall <hi>Caietane.</hi>
                  </hi> We are not heere to examine what the Cardinall did partly forbid, being dead and buried long before ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were made or could be thought upon, and was not liuing when any one of them was made. M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> proueth the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of them by the contents as is ſhewed, but if it be proued that they were vnlawful prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of things that were and are lawfull (although he had power to make ſuch decrees) the grounde of the neceſſitie of theſe which he hath made wil proue but a myer. The firſt Edict (made 17. Ianu. 1599. as we account) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth euery man vnder greeuous penalties <hi>ipſo fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> to bee incurred to divuldge any Bookes ſet out within two yeares before, or after to be ſet out, by which his lawfull eſtate ſhould be diſturbed, or the fame of any Eccleſiaſticall perſon of the Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by name be harmed. The cauſe of this decree was (as is therein ſpecified) that nothing ſhould be <hi>attempted, intermedled, or publiſhed among vs, that may be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue to our ſtate, or to the encreaſe of our troubles, or elſe to the detraction of our Bretheren.</hi> What if any man were ſo publikely iniured as he could not repaire his credite but by publiſhing? doth not the lawe of nature, and Nations, allow him that defence? how then did this decree containe a thing otherwiſe vnlawfull? but to come a litle nearer, was there not a Booke publiſhed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15701:20"/> and ſent into all parts of England, yea and beyond the ſeas by the Ieſuites, or their fauourites, Intituled in generall termes, <hi>Againſt the factious in the Church,</hi> but applied particularly to vs by the Archprieſt (as heere he confeſſeth in his anſwere to the fourth point) and can it be ſaid to be vnlawfull (if we had bene ſo idle) to publiſh in our owne defence againſt that ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and ſinfull Libell? Senceleſſe in running vpon diſobedience to the Sea Apoſtolike, from which no Letter came to commaund any thing, nor to teſtifie that any other had authoritie giuen to commaund. Sinfull in that vpon ſo weake a ground no wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was left vnlaid to our charge, nor any name of infamie omitted, and as now M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed confeſſeth in his anſwere to the fourth point in <hi>a matter of opinion, and therefore not worthie to make a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of contention which part ſoeuer was true.</hi> This Edict the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forbad not any thing otherwiſe vnlawfull, but only (as it ſhould ſeeme) gaue libertie to any our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to ſpread abroad any thing to the encreaſe of troubles, and detraction of the bretheren, and debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs only to publiſh againſt the detractious Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of others, howe iuſt ſoeuer our cauſe might bee.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Edict or Decree made the 29. of May, 1600. forbiddeth vnder penalties <hi>ipſo facto</hi> to be incurred, that no man <hi>directly or indirectly maintaine or defend in word or in writing the cenſure of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi>
                  </hi> (which had cleared vs from ſchiſme and ſinne, in our forbearing for a time to accept him in that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15701:21"/> vpon cauſes there ſet downe) <hi>whether it were truly giuen or forged, whether vpon true information or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi> Can it be iudged by any of reaſon to be a thing vnlawful in it ſelfe to defend a cenſure of the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Vniuerſitie in the world, being giuen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true information as heare he ſuppoſeth it might be? the preſumption is ſo great in this prohibition, and the decree ſo euidently conuinced to bee of a thing not vnlawfull, as wee need not heere to ſtay any longer vpon it.</p>
               <p>The third Decree, dated the 18. of Octob. 1600. conteineth many prohibitions, but that which M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> ſeemeth here moſt to vrge, is the prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that no man ſhould ask an other or giue his owne name to any thing, with which he or two of his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants were not firſt made acquainted. And I incline to thinke that hee meaneth this rather then the reſt, for that conformably to his aſſertion in this place, he ſaid (a litle after this Edict was made) that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Caietane</hi> did meane heereby that they who would giue their names to any thing, ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquaint the Archprieſt therewith, but alſo get his conſent therevnto: ſo that if the Prieſts would by common ſuffrage haue any thing amended in him, or any of thoſe, whom he thinketh to be his friends, or ſhould attempt any thing neceſſary to be done in ſuch place, where a bedroll of names ouerpeaſe (as they haue found by experience) be the cauſe neuer ſo iuſt, they cannot giue their names vnto it without his conſent. Now do I appeale to any honeſt man, whether it be a thing in it ſelfe vnlawfull for any to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15701:21"/> giue their names, or demaund others to any thing, which in reaſon they may thinke neceſſary for the common good of Gods Church, or reliefe of their owne miſeries? and if in ſuch a caſe it be not a thing vnlawfull, howe is this true, which Maiſter <hi>Blackwell</hi> heere affirmeth, that his decrees containe nothing but prohibition of things otherwiſe vnlawful? Now that we haue ſhewed that the things prohibited were not vnlawfull, but rather his prohibitions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently his firſt reaſon of the neceſſitie of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of no force, let vs ſee how the euent prooueth the neceſſitie of them. Some who carry graie haires, (and if they would keepe ſilence might goe for verie graue men, and thought fit to be Councellours) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer their want too much of that wiſedome, and learning which they might haue, and vpon theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees blunder it out (ſo as <hi>Will Sommers</hi> might finde them) that who ſo readeth the Bookes ſet out by the Prieſts (by warrant of all iuſt lawes) in the defence of their good name, and fame moſt iniuriouſly taken from them by the ſeditious Libell of F. <hi>Liſter,</hi> and the ſinfull vſe of others their tongues, is excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Had any excommunication bene threatned (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Archprieſt could not doo it) or had any prohibition bene made in the decrees that no man ſhould read any of our bookes, ſuch graue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might haue dreamed of ſuch matters as they talke on, but there being no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either of the one, or the other in any edicts, how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth Grauity (where litle time, hath bin or is ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in other ſtudies) to make ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Nownes &amp; Verbes, <hi>It is excommunication to read any of theſe bookes?</hi> Some are alſo ſaid to be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15701:22"/> for bringing a Prieſt a Breuiary to ſay his houres. Some carry ſcrowles about of ſuch Prieſtes names as muſt not be dealt withall. Some will not heare their confeſſions. Some teach that it is excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be preſent at their maſſe. And for what? forſooth for maintaining an opinion which was not <hi>worthie to make a matter of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which part ſoeuer is true:</hi> and ſeeking by lawfull appeale to the Sea Apoſtolike to haue the controuerſie fully decided?</p>
               <p>The Archprieſt inflicte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paines <hi>ipſo facto</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſcandals and ſeditions, either thoſe are no ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals and ſeditions, which are taken for ſuch, or they are very meanly preuented. But by what authoritie are penalties inflicted <hi>ipſo facto</hi> by him who through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath his order ſet downe vnto him for his proceedings, that is, <hi>to admoniſh, reprehend, and chaſtiſe alſo when néed ſhall be by abridging faculties, or if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie require by recalling the faculties.</hi> And afterward, <hi>If any ſhewe himſelfe diſobedient, vnquiet, or contumacious,</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may <hi>after due admonitions and reprehenſions made with bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly charitie puniſh him with Eccleſiaſticall penalties; that is to ſay by taking away his faculties, or by ſuſpenſion, vntill he amend.</hi> How is this order kept in the Archprieſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, when without any reprehenſion, or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly admonition after a fault, he will ſcant hold his hand vntill the fault be committed, but <hi>ipſo facto</hi> the offendour is puniſhed and how by any degrees for example, by hauing his faculties abridged, and after if neceſſitie require it, by leeſing them, or after this by being ſuſpended? no ſuch matter. But all at once <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> yea and more then this, hee is interdicted, for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15701:22"/> which there is no warrant in all the Commiſſion; wherefore and alſo for that the Archprieſt did not obſerue the order preſcribed him (being but a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delegat vnder the Card. <hi>Caietane</hi> as appeareth in his Letters) all which hee hath done in this kinde is of it ſelfe voyd,<note place="margin">Cap. cum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecta de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptis gloſſa ibidem. Cap. venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili de officio &amp; pot. iud. del. Hoſtienſis de offic. Iudicis deleg. num. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; <hi>10.</hi> Innoc. in cap. praedicta. S. Antonin. p. <hi>3.</hi> tit. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>3. § 1.</hi> &amp; <hi>10.</hi> Gemin. cap. Quia ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficali de off. &amp; pot. Iud. del. in. <hi>6.</hi> Ang. Arm. Sil. verb. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legatus.</note> as it is manifeſt by the rules of holie Church, and thoſe who comment thereon, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no good euent (if there had bene any) could proue the lawfulnes of his decrees. But he could not wel haue the vſe of <hi>forum contentioſum,</hi> nor <hi>cyte or produce witneſſes, nor conueniently méete with euery one <hi>poſt factum.</hi>
                  </hi> Were they who put him in authoritie ignorant that heere could not be any formall Court kept? or can M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> ſay, that he cannot meet with anie one <hi>poſt factum,</hi> either himſelfe, or by his Aſſiſtants, who in his Letters to his Aſſiſtants, giueth directions to examine ſuch, as whoſe names are to the appeale, vpon ſuch and ſuch points? If he wil denie that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath written to particular Gentlemen to giue entertainment to ſuch a man in particular to examine the Prieſt there reſident concerning his ſubſcribing to the appeale, and concerning his puniſhment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, his owne Letters ſhall be brought out againſt him? ſo that if it pleaſe him, it is euident inough that he can proceed <hi>poſt factum,</hi> and therefore this is but a poore ſhift for the making of his decrees in ſuch ſort, as they are with penalties, <hi>ipſo facto</hi> to be incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. As for the good which he hath done by theſe his cenſures, it hath bene no other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make ſome diſſemble for a while, becauſe they would not be ſaid to be ſuſpended, or to haue loſt their faculties. And
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15701:23"/> perplexe men whether they may in this time of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution goe for the Sacraments. And for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his decrees, he may ſay that he proceedeth vpon other cauſe then vpon the appeale, but then he muſt promiſe comfort to ſuch as heere hee taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice haue need thereof, vpon ſome other cauſe, then the ſubſcribing, or hauing their names put to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, for this is an euident argument (whatſoeuer is pretended) that ſome haue had need of comfort for that act doing, but the words of his Letter dated 16. Aprill, 1601. to a Laie Gentleman, leaue no place for any doubt in this cauſe. <hi>This I write</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to make you priuie of the great ſpirituall daunger, wherein you and all that receiue any Sacraments of M. <hi>Oſ. N.</hi> may be, if it be ſo that he hath ſubſcribed vnto a ſeditious Pamphlet, coloured with the name of an Appeale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The oath of obedience exacted by the Archprieſt is beyond his Commiſſion. And the leſſe to be liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, for that it is exacted as a ſatisfaction due to him by ſuch, as haue appealed to <hi>Rome,</hi> vpon no other cauſes, then were prooued out of his owne Letters, and others of his Councell, and are of that quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that neither he nor all his complices in thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will euer be able to make condigne ſatisfaction to the Prieſts.</p>
               <p>And here I could wiſh that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were not ſo caried away with the ſound of authoritie, hauing had ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient knowledge of the Prieſts their carriage toward all lawfull authoritie by their behauiour at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Breue, and let not the name of a ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous booke (the leaſt point therein contained not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15701:23"/> to be controld, but by ſecret whiſperings where it ſhall not come to the examination) put men from ſeeing how they are deluded by ſuch as meane them no good, but labour now to lull them a ſleep till they haue gotten what they would, &amp; to this end bebarre them of all ſuch helpes, as whereby they might be enformed of the truth. The points neither confute themſelues, nor will be confuted by any. Neither are the bookes written in paſſion, but to moue all ſincere Catholikes to haue compaſſion both of themſelues, and of vs, when they ſhall ſee by theſe diſcourſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe hands their ſoules are, and how ſlight rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning is made of the infamie of ſo many Prieſts for <hi>a matter not worthie to make a matter of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention which part ſoeuer is true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the names to the appeale. Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſome doo comfort themſelues, they will hardly finde any whoſe name was there without his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, for although perchance there were ſome cauſes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to ſome, which were not knowne to the reſt, yet in the chief they all found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues agreeued, and deſired remedie by way of appeale, to which they ſet to their hands, or ſent their conſent by others to haue their names ſet too, for which the Authours will be brought foorth if need require, to iuſtifie their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, whoſe names they cauſed to be ſubſcribed: and ſince this matter came in queſtion we haue to ſhewe the conſents of ſome vnder their owne handes, of whom the doubt was made.</p>
               <p>But to grow to amend, all are to vnderſtand, that our deſire is to haue peace, and for peace ſake haue
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15701:24"/> we publiſhed theſe bookes, knowing that there is no way ſo meet to worke an vnfained peace, as to haue the truth knowne of theſe proceedings, that thereby the ſoare may be ſearched to the quick, &amp; not healed as it was before, and brake out againe preſently after, by the indiſcretion of F. <hi>Iones</hi> a Ieſuite, who, when all were quiet, affirmed that they incurred the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of holie Church, who ſhould ſay <hi>Dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizando</hi> that we were not Schiſmatickes. If we were Schiſmatickes we refuſe not to ſtand to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church. If we were not, we deſire it may ſo be declared, as there be no more ſtrife raiſed thereon here in England, or elſewhere. F. <hi>Garnet</hi> the head of the Ieſuites, made lately a motion for peace, which if it had come from the Archprieſt, or if hee had ioyned with F. <hi>Garnet</hi> therein, it might haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſome effect, becauſe theſe controuerſies were as well with the Archprieſt, as the Ieſuits. But the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt not ioyning in this treatie which was begunne by the other, the Prieſts could not thinke that it was ſincerely meant, in which they are now confirmed, becauſe ſo ſoone as Fa. <hi>Garnet</hi> vnderſtood by M. <hi>R. B.</hi> the 27. of Iuly, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions made at the firſt attonement were not as yet performed by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt,<note place="margin">The recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of M. D. Biſhop, &amp; M. Charnock home from baniſhment and confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> he noted for a partie in this controuerſie, and that ſomewhat was expected, to the ſame effect from the Archprieſt (whom this matter moſt concerned) he miſtooke it for a refuſall to haue a parley of peace, and ſo ſignified it to a friend of his, vpon the laſt of Iuly; beſide that in theſe Letters laſt written by the Archprieſt to his aſſiſtants in anſwere of our bookes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15701:24"/> (doubleſſe not without the priuitie of Fa. <hi>Garnet,</hi> whoſe counſell he is to haue in matters of moment) he declareth his opinion which ſtill he retaineth that we were ſchiſmatikes, in the which renewing of ſo grieuous an infamie if we ſtir, it is not without cauſe, for we lie ſtill open thereby to thoſe iniuries, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull ſpeeches which were vſed by Fa. <hi>Liſter</hi> in his libel, &amp; are now ſo in the faſhion abroad, that the fayreſt Catholike houſen haue now the filthieſt aire, and all baſe ſcoldes who haue the moſt impudent clackes, muſt giue place to their betters.</p>
               <p>But as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Diligentibus deum omnia cooperantur in bonum: <hi>All things turne to their good, who loue God,</hi>
                  </hi> which I hope we do, in ſeeking his glorie as F. <hi>Garnet</hi> knoweth we do, and witneſſeth as much in his Letters dated vpon Midſommer day laſt paſt, and his glorie is our content, and in him we hope to haue peace, which alſo we wiſh to thoſe who in their owne conſciences haue giuen vs the greateſt cauſe of offence, and pray for them, as we deſire the praier of all good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes for vs.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:15701:25"/>
            <p>After that this anſwere to M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> his Letter was printed, an other copie of the ſame letter came to our ſight, which hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs to amend the firſt copie by way of <hi>Errata,</hi> although it contain nothing of moment more then the firſt, except that in the <hi>6.</hi> Page in the end of the firſt clauſe in anſwere to the firſt point theſe words are wanting. <hi>It toucheth the greater part and better part of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany there.</hi> To which if we would imitate others in their inſolent compariſons, we might ſay (and perchance with more truth) that the leſſer part was the better, and anſwer to that of the greater part, <hi>Stultorum infinitus eſt numerus.</hi> The world is full of Fooles. But remembring that ſaying of the Apoſtle, Rom. <hi>14. What are you who iudge an others ſeruant?</hi> We can conclude no otherwiſe then the ſame Apoſtle concluded, <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>10. He is approued, whom God commendeth.</hi> In the ſame <hi>6.</hi> Page lin. <hi>23.</hi> where <hi>(greateſt)</hi> muſt be put in place of <hi>(moſt grieuouſly)</hi> (a word not likely to be ſo much miſtake) the ſence might giue that the Pope is contemned by the complaint of the vſage of the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, if F. <hi>Parſons</hi> (as at other times) in his Letters to F. <hi>Holt,</hi> dated <hi>15.</hi> May, <hi>1597.</hi> did not confeſſe that he found errors in the Ieſuites their carriage toward the Schollers, and ſuch, as if many of thoſe things had happened in their quieteſt Colledge in <hi>Spaine</hi> or <hi>Flaunders,</hi> they would haue put the peace out of ioynt.</p>
            <p>Alſo page <hi>8.</hi> in the margent <hi>Zecchius de rep eccle.</hi> is left out, who in his Treatiſe <hi>de ſtatu Ill. D. Card.</hi> Num <hi>9.</hi> handling the office of a Protector, ſaith not one word concerning his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 6 lin. 4. their. the other. l. 12 being. long. l. 15 It concerneth. It no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerneth our l. 19. miſlike. inſtituted. l. 23. moſt grieuouſly grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. pa. 7 l. 2. accept execute. l. 3. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered. learned. l. 27. not. not as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. pag. 8. l. 4. the beſt. the opinion of the beſt. ibib. credited. credited dutifully, l. 16. Agents. Prieſts. l. 22. any. any one. l. 30. cauſe. cauſe otherwiſe. marg. Strozzeus. Sbrozeus. Zecchius de rep. eccleſ. pag. 9 li. 9 an. and. l. 19. now. more. l. 21. The. Other. l. 26. ſlanderous. ſcandalous. l. 30. you. you all. pag. 10 lin. 3. and. our. lin. 7. this our. this. 11. 23. 73. pag. 33. lin. 30. Strozz. read Sbroz.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15701:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
